A Guide to the Brooke Family Papers, 1650-1835
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Brooke Family Papers, 1650-1835
The Library of Virginia
22077
53 leaves and 85 pages
Brooke Family
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Purchased from Mrs. R. C. Power, Richmond, Virginia, January 1943.
Biographical Information
The Brooke family was prominent in Essex County, Virginia, during the 17th, 18th, and 19th centuries. Several branches of the family lived in the county, and one became known as the Taliaferro Brooke family because of intermarriage with the Taliaferros. One of those marriages was between William Brooke (d. 1734) and Sarah Taliaferro Brooke (d. 1763). The Brookes owned a great amount of property in Essex County and several of its members held offices in the county government.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1650-1835, of the Brooke family of Essex County, Virginia, consisting of agreements, bonds, deeds, decrees, depositions, land grants, powers of attorney, plats, receipts, reports, surveys, wills, and writs of commission. Most of these papers are deeds, grants and surveys, the rest deal with land title transfers in some manner. Eight of the records predate the existence of Essex County, and are from York and Rappahannock Counties, Virginia, when Essex was part of them in the 17th century.
Contents List
- Land grant, 14 September 1650, for 600 acres on the south side of the Rappahannock River issued to Richard Coleman by Governor William Berkeley.
- Land grant, 14 September 1650, for 600 acres on the south side of the Rappahannock River issued to Richard Coleman by Governor William Berkeley.
- Land grant, 14 November 1650, for 600 acres on the south side of the Rappahannock River issued to Richard Coleman by Governor William Berkeley.
- Land grant, 19 February 1662, for 627 acres on the south side of the Rappahannock River issued to Thomas Hawkins by Governor William Berkeley.
- Deed, dated 29 May 1665 and recorded 7 June[?] 1665, for 444 acres in (Old) Rappahannock County, Virginia, from Richard West to William Fogg, both of Rappahannock County.
- Deed, September 1673, for [1050?] acres in (Old) Rappahannock County from Andrew Gilson of Stafford County to Edward Stafford of (Old) Rappahannock County.
- Deed, dated 8 July 1675 and recorded 1 September 1675, for 100 acres in (Old) Rappahannock County from Edward Stafford to Daniel Shipley, both of (Old) Rappahannock County.
- Power of attorney, dated 19 June 1675 and recorded 4 September 1675, from Andrew Gilson of Stafford County to Thomas Hawkins.
- Power of attorney, 8 September 1692, from Daniel Shipley of Essex County, Virginia, to his wife Alice Shipley.
- Deed, dated 1 August 1693 and recorded 10 August 1693, for his share of 600 acres in Essex County from Richard Dison to William Browne, both of Essex County.
- Deed, dated 4 January 1693/4 and recorded 10 May 1695, for [7?]4 acres in Essex County from William Browne to David Wilson, both of Essex County.
- Will, dated 15 January 1700 and recorded 10 April 1701, of William Bendry of Essex County.
- Deed, 4 December 1701, for a plantation and 100 acres in [Essex County] from William Thompson of Westmoreland County, Virginia, to Isaac Flowers.
- Deed, 15 October 1702, for 200 acres in [Essex County] from Dorothy North of Gloucester County, Virginia, to Isaac Flowers.
- Land grant, 2 November 1705, for 170 acres in Essex County issued to Isaac Flowers by Governor Edward Nott.
- Deed, dated 3 August 1706 and recorded 10 August 1706, for land in Essex County from Robert Beeswell and Sarah Beeswell to Isaac Flowers.
- Deed, dated and recorded 10 March 1706/7, for 660 acres in Essex County from Daniel Henry and his wife Dorothy Henry to William Thompson, all of Essex County.
- Deposition, 25 April 1707, of Richard Jefferson and Johanna Jefferson stating that Dorothy North had signed a paper for Isaac Flowers 15 October 1702.
- Deed, 9 June 1708, for 200 acres in Essex County from Samuel Henshaw to [Aylee?] Shiple.
- Deed, dated 6 September 1708 and recorded 10 September 1708, for 75 acres in Essex County from Henry Long, Richmond, County, Virginia, to Thomas Plummer of Gloucester County.
- Deed, dated 2 March 1709/10 and recorded 10 March 1709/10, for 146 acres in Essex County from Thomas Short, Essex County, to Richard Kemp, Middlesex County, Virginia.
- Report, 25 February 1713, of committee in the suit of John Boughan, Susanna his wife, Thomas Ley, and Augustine Ley vs. Mary Flowers.
- Report, 3 December 1713, of committee in the suit of John Boughan, Susanna his wife, Thomas Ley, and Augustine Ley vs. Mary Flowers.
- Bond, 19 July 1714, from JOhn Boughan and Thomas Ley to Mary Flowers.
- Deed of lease, dated 20 May 1723 and 18 June 1723, for 296 acres in Essex County from Edward Evans and Anne Evans to William Brooke, all of Essex County.
- Deed of release, dated 21 May 1723 and 18 June 1723, for 296 acres in Essex County from Edward Evans and Anne Evans to William Brooke, all of Essex County.
- Report, 23 January 1724, of committee in the division of land of William Brooke and Richard Gatewood.
- Deed, 25 September 1724, for land in Essex County from Elizabeth Wilson to William Brooke, both of Essex County.
- Bond, 20 September 1725, from William Brooke to Richard Gatewood, both of Essex County.
- Deed of lease, 19 February 1727, for 56 acres in Essex County from Edward Murra and Martha Murra to William Brooke, all of Essex County.
- Deed of release, 20 February 1727, from Edward Murra and Martha Murra to William Brooke, all of Essex County.
- Survey, 26 March 1726, for 1080 acres in Spotsylvania County, Virginia, for George Braxton by James Taylor, surveyor.
- Land grants, 28 September 1728, for 1000 acres in Spotsylvania County from King George II to George Braxton. Two copies.
- Deed, 2 October 1725, for 170 acres in Essex County from Edward Murrin, Essex County, to William Robinson, King George County, Virginia. Assignment, 24 April 1730, from William Robinson to William Brooke.
- Deed, dated 15 November 1730 and 17 November 1730, for 170 acres in Essex County from Edward Murrough and Martha Murrough to William Brooke, all of Essex County.
- Deed, 20 December 1731, for 86 acres in Essex County from Rice Brocke, King and Queen County, Virginia, to William Brooke, Essex County.
- Survey, 12 March 1732, of 72 1/2 acres in Essex County belonging to William Brooke, by R. Brooke, surveyor.
- Bond, 28 November 1733, from Thomas Plummer to William Brooke, both of Essex County.
- Bond, 17 June 1734, from Thomsa Plummer, Richmond County, Virginia, to Sarah Brooke, Essex County.
- Deed, dated 17 June 1734 and recorded 18 June 1734, for 75 acres in Essex County from Thomas Plummer, Richmond County, to Sarah Brooke, Essex County.
- Receipt, 1735, to Sarah Brooke for payment for probate of [William] Brooke's will.
- Receipt, 26 March 1735, from Thomas Gatewood to Sarah Brooke for payment of rent for 1734. Reverse contains note from W. Beverley to Reverend [Robert] Rose.
- Deed, dated 17 January 1736 and recorded 17 May 1737, for 170 acres in Essex County from John Rutherford and Mary Rutherford to William Short, all of Essex County.
- Survey, 30 December 1737, of 90 acres [in Essex County] belonging to William Short, by Robert Brooke, surveyor.
- Plat, 3 February 1742, of 577 1/2 acres belonging to William Brooke, deceased, and 173 acres belonging to Richard Gatewood, R. Brooke, surveyor.
- Deed of lease, 29 October 1743, for 200 acres in Essex County from Philip Davis and Hannah Davis, Goochland County, Virginia, to Sarah Brooke, Essex County.
- Deed of release, 30 October 1743, from Philip Davis and Hannah Davis of Goochland County to Sarah Brooke, Essex County.
- Notice, no date, by Alexander Cruden that William Gatewood, son of Richard and Franky Gatewood, was born 7 May 1745.
- Writ of commission, 10 July 1745, to Maxamilian Robison and Joseph Morton, justices of King George County.
- Deed of lease, dated 19 July 1745 and recorded 20 August 1745, for property in Essex County from Peter Jett and Keren Jett, King George County, to Sarah Brooke, Essex County.
- Deed of release, dated 19 July 1745 and recorded 20 August 1745, from Peter Jett and Keren Jett, King George County, to Sarah Brooke, Essex County.
- Writ of commission, 6 November 1746, to Joshua Fry and Charles Lynch, justices of the peace for Albemarle County, Virginia.
- Deed, dated 12 November 1746 and recorded 16 June 1747, for property in Essex County from Philip Davis and Hannah Davis, Albemarle County, to Sarah Brooke, Essex County.
- Account, June-November 1747, of Sarah Brooke with John Lee, clerk, Essex County.
- Receipt, May 1751, from John Lee, clerk, Essex County, to Sarah Brooke for payment for copies of William Brooke's will.
- Deed, dated 19 February 1753 and recorded 19 June 1753, for 170 acres in Essex County from William Short and Barbara Short to Sarah Brooke, all of Essex County.
- Bond, 26 October 1753, from Philip Davis, Albemarle County, to Sarah Brooke, Essex County.
- Receipt, 26 October 1753, from Philip Davis, Albemarle County, to Sarah Brooke, Essex County, for payment
- Deed, dated 20 March 1758 and recorded 15 April 1758, for 121 acres in Essex County from Sarah Miller to William Brooke, both of Essex County.
- Survey report, 16 December 1758, of Edward Vawter.
- Survey, 15 January 1759, of 263 acres belonging to Henry Motley, Essex County.
- Bond, 19 May 1759, from John Motley and Henry Motley to William Brooke, all of Essex County.
- Bond, 10 January 1760, from John Motley and Henry Motley to Jeremiah Bozwell, all of Essex County.
- Account, May 1760, of William Brooke with John Lee, clerk of Essex County.
- Deed of lease, dated 16 May 1760 and recorded 19 May 1760, for 263 acres in Essex County from John Motley to William Brooke, both of Essex County.
- Deed of release, dated 17 May 1760 and recorded 19 May 1760, from John Motley to William Brooke, both of Essex County.
- Order, 24 June 1760, from John Motley to William Brooke for payment.
- Survey, 26 February 1761, of 133 1/2 acres belonging to the estate of Richard Gatewood of Essex County, by Caleb Lindsey, surveyor.
- Deed, dated 18 February 1761 and recorded 20 July 1761, for land in Essex County from Robert Cole and Franky Cole to John Thomas, all of Essex County.
- Abstract, 4 October 1761, of a clause from the will of Richard Gatewood, Essex County.
- Agreement, 30 October 1761, for the sale of 133 1/2 acres in Essex County from William Gatewood to William Brooke, both of Essex County.
- Bond, 16 November 1761, from William Gatewood, John Latane, and William Gatewood to William Brooke.
- Bond, 22 December 1761, from William Brooke to William Gatewood.
- Receipt, 22 July 1762, from John Thomas to William Brooke for payment for purchase.
- Survey, 27 November 1762, of 509 acres belonging to William Brooke of Essex County by Caleb Lindsey, surveyor.
- Survey, 11 October 1766, of 150 acres in Essex County bought by William Brooke, deceased from Richard Gatewood, deceased, by R. Brooke, surveyor.
- Will, dated 22 August 1770 and recorded 21 January 1771, of Thomas Butler, Essex County.
- Deed, dated 29 September 1785 and recorded 18 April 1786 and 21 June 1790, for 156 acres in Essex County from Richard Hipkins and his daughters Mary, Charlotte, and Elizabeth Hipkins, all of Westmoreland County, to John Brooke, Essex County.
- Deed, recorded 18 July 1796, for property [in Essex County] from Thomas Boulware and Sukey Boulware to Thomas Smart. Document is incomplete and consists only of recordation information.
- Survey, 9 February 1797, of 133 acres belonging to Thomas Butler, Essex County, by Humphrey Brooke, surveyor.
- Deed, dated 24 April 1797 and recorded 18 December 1797, for 60 acres in Essex County from Thomas Butler, Frances Butler, and William Butler to John Porter. Includes writ of commission to Samuel Rust and George Garner, justices of Westmoreland County.
- Deed, dated 19 November 1798 and recorded 15 April 1799, for 133 acres in Essex County from Thomas Hodge and Catherine Hodge, Westmoreland County, to Robert Baylor, Essex County.
- Deed, dated 14 November 1798 and recorded 15 April 1799, for 60 acres in Essex County from John Porter and Mary Porter to Thomas Hodge, all of Westmoreland County.
- Decree, 17 February 1800, in suit of Ursula Sanford, an infant, by Robert Baylor, her next friend, against Patty and Catherine Sanford, infants, by William Butler, their guardian, Essex County.
- Deed, dated 4 September 1800 and recorded 15 September 1800, for 4 1/2 acres from William Hawkins to Robert Baylor, both of Essex County.
- Deed, dated [-] March 1801 and recorded 21 September 1801, for land in Essex County from Rosanna Ayres to Robert Baylor, both of Essex County.
- Deed, dated 20 December 1802 and recorded 20 December 1802, for 140 acres in Essex County from William Howard and Elizabeth Howard to Robert Baylor, all of Essex County.
- Deed, dated 8 October 1835 and recorded 16 November 1835, for 140 acres in Essex County from Richard Baylor, Lucy Baylor, William Baylor, and Alexander T. Baylor of Essex County and Baynham Baylor and Eliza Baylor of Norfolk, Virginia, to William T. Brooke of Essex County.
- Abstracts, no date, of a deed for 150 acres from Paine to Kemp and of a deed for 146 acres from Short to Kemp.
- Plat, no date, for 140 acres in Essex County called Smart's. See deeds of 20 December 1802 and 8 October 1835.